Finding Aid for the Vachel Lindsay Papers LSC.0754
UCLA Library Special Collections
Vachel Lindsay papers
1910-1929
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lindsay, Vachel
LSC.0754
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Nicholas Vachel Lindsay (1879-1931) was a highly successful poet on recital tours, especially from 1914-1920. His Collected Poems appeared in 1923. The collection consists of letters of Lindsay to Wilhelm Miller and family, manuscripts, scrapbooks, ephemera, and presentation copies of books by Lindsay. There are also ephemera and newspaper clippings by or relating to Lindsay.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mary Rogers Miller, 1962.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9922210053606533
Biography
Nicholas Vachel Lindsay was born on November 10, 1879 in Springfield, Illinois; attended Hiram College for three years, then studied art in New York with Robert Henri; walked from Illinois to New Mexico, reading his poems in exchange for food and lodging; in 1913 his poem, General William Booth Enters into Heaven, appeared in Harriet Monroe's magazine, Poetry; other poems include The Congo (1914), Abraham Lincoln Walks at Midnight (1914), The Santa Fe Trail (1914), The Chinese Nightingale (1917), Bryan, Bryan, Bryan, Bryan (1920), The Golden Age of Springfield (1920), The Flower-Fed Buffaloes (1926), and Johnny Appleseed (1928); was highly successful on recital tours, especially from 1914-1920; his Collected Poems appeared in 1923; he died on December 5, 1931 in Springfield, Illinois.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of letters of Lindsay to Wilhelm Miller and family, manuscripts, scrapbooks, ephemera, and presentation copies of books by Lindsay. Includes a presentation copy to the Wilhelm Millers of The Village Magazine (March 1911, the only number ever issued) with holograph annotations, a copy of Vision (Spring 1912) containing Lindsay's article, The New Localism, with his illustrations and several holograph and typescript poems on the other pages. Also contains a presentation copy of his Rhymes to be Traded for Bread, and his copy of The Art of the Moving Picture (1915), with copious annotations and corrections. There are also ephemera and newspaper clippings by or relating to Lindsay.
Poets, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Lindsay, Vachel, 1879-1931--Archives.
- Letters to Wilhelm Miller, and family. Springfield, Illinois., 1913-1929.; Holograph. 4 items. (Box 1)
- Vision, village number, no.4. Pennsylvania., 1912.; 1 item. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains 6 illustrations by Lindsay, and was used by him as a scrapbook for poems: holograph, typescript, and clipped printed verses with holograph notes throughout. Includes a copy of Rhymes to be Traded for Bread, and one broadside, The Sangamon County Place Advocate, no.1, Springfield, Illinois, Christmas, 1909, by Lindsay.
  Presentation copy to Wilhelm Miller, Springfield, Illinois, October 15, 1913.
- Rhymes to Be Traded for Bread, Springfield, Illinois., June 1912.; 2 items. (Box 1)
  A small book of 8 leaves, unbound, ... to be used in exchange for the necessities of life on a tramp-journey from the author's home town, through the West and back...
  One of the copies is inscribed, Wilhelm Miller from N.V. Lindsay, and is marked throughout.
- Adventures While Preaching the Gospel of Beauty. Chapters 2, 4-6. Forum., 1913-1914.; 4 items. (Box 1)
  Some holograph notations. Chapters extracted from Forum, a periodical, are:
  - Walking through Missouri
  - In Kansas: The First Harvest
  - In Kansas: The Second and Third Harvest
  - The End of the Road, Moonshine, and an Epilogue
- Clipped articles by or re Lindsay. v.p., v.d.; 9 items. (Box 1)
  - Vachel Lndsay, by Arthur Waugh, 2 columns from a British newspaper.
  - Proclamation! by Lindsay, one page from Rural Manhood, New York., June 1913.
  - The New Localism by Lindsay, one page from Twentieth Century Magazine, n.p.
  - Proclamation of the Gospel of Beauty, n.p., n.d.
  - Four illustrations: The Village Improvement Parade, sections 1-4, n.p., 1910.
- The Village Magazine. Springfield, Illinois., 1911.; 1 item. 29 cm. (Box 1)
  Inscription, in ink, inside front cover: To Wilhelm Miller:-with all good wishes. This being my last battered copy of the model for a village magazine... the date, in pencil, is October 16, 1913. Contains holograph remarks about some of the poems; also, on outside front cover, notes in ink, pencil state: By N.V. Lindsay...Reviewed in Current Literature for March 1911...Only one number ever issued.
- General William Booth Enters into Heaven and Other Poems.... New York: Mithchell Kennerley., 1913.; 19.5 cm. Red boards. (Box 1)
  Picture of Lindsay is pasted inside front cover. Inscription in holograph: Mary Rogers Miller, from W.M., December 25, 1913.
- The Art of the Moving Picture. New York: the Macmillan Company., 19 cm. Buff-green-black boards. (Box 1)
  Includes a long dedication to my dear Miller...Vachel, January 5, 1915, Springfield, Illinois. Also: author's extensive underlinings and margin notations throughout, as well as a clipped article, Better 'Movies' for Children, by E. Leslie Gilliams.